Register of the Clark University Library collection
Hoover Institution Archives
Clark University Library collection
1914-1920
XX666
Hoover Institution Archives
4 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize box (2.5 linear feet)
Pamphlets, leaflets, newspaper articles, proclamations, letters, miscellaneous propaganda forms, memorabilia, and photographs relating to American neutrality and subsequent participation in World War I. Includes proofs of war loan appeals and German propaganda banners. Collected by Clark University Library.
Clark Univeristy (Worcester, Mass.) Library.
Access
The collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Historical Note
Clark University is a private American university and liberal arts college founded in Worcester, Massachussetts in 1887. It is the oldest educational institution founded as an all-graduate university in the United States. Clark College opened for undergraduates in 1902 and was managed independently from Clark University until 1920.
Scope and Content of Collection
The Clark University Library collection contains pamphlets, leaflets, newspaper articles, proclamations, letters, various propaganda forms, memorabilia, and photographs relating to American neutrality and subsequent participation in World War I. The collection also includes proofs of war loan appeals and German propaganda banners. These materials were collected by Clark University Library.
Clark University (Worcester, Mass.) Library.; Propaganda, American.; Propaganda, German.; United States--Neutrality.; World War, 1914-1918--Propaganda.; World War, 1914-1918--United States.
- Correspondence, 1914-1922
  Scope and Contents note
  The majority of the correspondence within this collection was sent to Louis Wilson, the librarian of Clark University.
  - Received by Louis Wilson, 1914-1920
    - 1914 (Box-folder 1: 1)
    - 1915 (Box-folder 1: 2)
    - 1916 (Box-folder 1: 3)
    - 1917 (Box-folder 1: 4)
    - 1918-1920 (Box-folder 1: 5)
  - Sent, 1914-1922
    - Allies Relief Committee, 1916 (Box-folder 1: 6)
    - American Association of Advertising Agencies, 1918 (Box-folder 1: 7)
    - The American Central Committee for Russian Relief, undated (Box-folder 1: 8)
    - American Committee of the French Heroes Fund, 1917 (Box-folder 1: 9)
    - American Legion, undated (Box-folder 1: 10)
    - The American Rights League, 1916 (Box-folder 1: 11)
    - American Truth Society, undated (Box-folder 1: 12)
    - Atlantic Union, 1916 (Box-folder 1: 13)
    - Books and periodicals, 1914-1916 (Box-folder 1: 14)
    - The British Imperial Relief Fund, 1916 (Box-folder 1: 15)
    - Chamber of German-American Commerce, Inc., 1915 (Box-folder 1: 16)
    - Clark College Ambulance Unit, 1917 (Box-folder 1: 17)
    - Committee on University and College Resources, 1917 (Box-folder 1: 18)
    - Department of Labor, 1918 (Box-folder 1: 19)
    - Department of State, 1916 (Box-folder 1: 20)
    - Federal Trade Commission, 1916 (Box-folder 1: 21)
    - The Fighting Fourth Liberty Loan, undated (Box-folder 1: 22)
    - French Heroes Lafayette Memorial Fund, Inc., 1920 (Box-folder 1: 23)
    - General Relief Committee, 1920 (Box-folder 1: 24)
    - Hydrographic Department, 1916 (Box-folder 1: 25)
    - Librairie Terquom, 1914-1915 (Box-folder 1: 26)
    - Library of Congress, 1915 (Box-folder 1: 27)
    - The Loyal Coalition, 1920 (Box-folder 1: 28)
    - Military enrollment, 1917 (Box-folder 1: 29)
    - National Allied Relief Committee, 1920 (Box-folder 1: 30)
    - Office of the Insurance Officer, 1919 (Box-folder 1: 31)
    - Ordnance Department, U.S. Army, 1918 (Box-folder 1: 32)
    - Organization of American Women for Strict Neutrality, 1915 (Box-folder 1: 33)
    - Park Trust Company, 1917 (Box-folder 1: 34)
    - Permanent Blind Relief War Fund, 1916, 1920 (Box-folder 1: 35)
    - The Red Cross, 1918 (Box-folder 1: 36)
    - Refugees in Paris Fund, undated (Box-folder 1: 37)
    - Russian Information Bureau, 1920 (Box-folder 1: 38)
    - Russian relief, 1916-1922 (Box-folder 1: 39)
    - Society of the Ten Allies, 1916 (Box-folder 2: 1)
    - Soviet Russia Medical Relief Committee, 1920 (Box-folder 2: 2)
    - Viernick's, The American Monthly "Feed and Clothe Germany" Department, undated (Box-folder 2: 3)
    - War Department, 1916, 1918 (Box-folder 2: 4)
    - The War Relief Clearing House, 1914-1915 (Box-folder 2: 5)
    - Wilson, Louis, 1917 (Box-folder 2: 6)
    - The World's Court League, Inc., 1916 (Box-folder 2: 7)
- Clark University Files, undated (Box-folder 2: 8)
- Maps, undated (Box-folder 2: 9)
- Memorabilia, 1911-1920
  - Bookmarks, undated (Box-folder 5: 1)
    Contains a variety of silk bookmarks in plastic cases.
  - Belgian tags, 1916 (Box-folder 2: 10)
  - Blank journal, undated (Box-folder 2: 11)
  - Boston City Club card, 1919 (Box-folder 2: 12)
  - Brooch, undated (Box-folder 2: 13)
  - Calendar of the Little House of Saint-Pantaleon, 1920 (Box-folder 2: 14)
  - The Canadian Patriotic Fund buttons, undated (Box-folder 2: 15)
  - Certificate, 1918 (Box-folder 2: 16)
  - Certificate of enrollment, U.S. Shipyard Volunteers, undated (Box-folder 2: 17)
  - Dr. Blakeslee's History seminar, 1917 (Box-folder 2: 18)
  - Italian Flag tag, 1919 (Box-folder 2: 19)
  - National Flag of China Republic, 1911 (Box-folder 2: 20)
  - Patriotic Fund supporter tags, 1918 (Box-folder 2: 21)
  - Post cards, undated (Box-folder 2: 22)
  - Red Cross Benefit theatre ticket, 1918 (Box-folder 2: 23)
  - Save a Soldier Fund, 1917 (Box-folder 2: 24)
  - Shipyard Volunteer pin, undated (Box-folder 2: 25)
  - Stamps, undated (Box-folder 2: 26)
  - United States Government thrift card, 1918 (Box-folder 2: 27)
  - War Chest tags, 1918 (Box-folder 2: 28)
  - Worcester pin, undated (Box-folder 2: 29)
- Photographs, 1917
  - Clark University Ambulance Unit, 1917 (Box-folder 2: 30)
- Printed Matter, 1914-1920
  - Pamphlets, 1914-1920
    - Above the Battle, undated (Box-folder 3: 1)
    - And He Wore on His Coat a Red Cross Button, undated (Box-folder 3: 2)
    - Appeal of the Royal Hungarian Francis Joseph University to the Universities of the Civilized World, 1920 (Box-folder 3: 3)
    - The Atlantic Unit, 1915 (Box-folder 3: 4)
    - Ayesha von Kapitanleutnant v. Mucke, undated (Box-folder 3: 5)
    - Books Definitely Bearing on the Nations Involved in the European War, undated (Box-folder 3: 6)
    - Books of Current Interest, undated (Box-folder 3: 7)
    - Books of the Hour in the Wanamaker Book Store, undated (Box-folder 3: 8)
    - Brockton Public Library Quarterly Bulletin, 1914 (Box-folder 3: 9)
    - Bull, 1916 (Box-folder 3: 10)
    - "Bull" the Financial Proposition, 1916 (Box-folder 3: 11)
    - C.A.F. KAHLBAUM, 1914 (Box-folder 3: 12)
    - The Call to Raise a War Fund of $100,000,000, 1917 (Box-folder 3: 13)
    - Carry On!, undated (Box-folder 3: 14)
    - Cecil Fanning the Celebrated Baritone, undated (Box-folder 3: 15)
    - A Challenge to Christians in the Churches of America, undated (Box-folder 3: 16)
    - The Church of the Unity, 1917 (Box-folder 3: 17)
    - Deutsche Kriegs-Literatur, undated (Box-folder 3: 18)
    - The Devil Has Resigned, 1917 (Box-folder 3: 19)
    - A Directory of the World Alliance for Promoting International Friendship Through the Churches, undated (Box-folder 3: 20)
    - The Enoch Pratt Free Library, 1914 (Box-folder 3: 21)
    - Europe and War, undated (Box-folder 3: 22)
    - The European War: Some Interesting and Timely MacMillan Books, undated (Box-folder 3: 23)
    - Eyewitness Picture of Scenes in Belgium and Northern France, undated (Box-folder 3: 24)
    - Facts about Liberty Bonds, undated (Box-folder 3: 25)
    - Five Little Pigs and How Four Made Money for Farm Girls and Boys, undated (Box-folder 3: 26)
    - For Strong, Brave Men Only, undated (Box-folder 3: 27)
    - He Bought a Bond and Gave His Life, undated (Box-folder 3: 28)
    - How the Soldier Keeps His Nerve, undated (Box-folder 3: 29)
    - Hymns and Prayers for Our Country, undated (Box-folder 3: 30)
    - An Invitation to Membership in a World Organization, 1918 (Box-folder 3: 31)
    - La Guerre, undated (Box-folder 3: 32)
    - Last Will and Testament of the Kaiser, 1918 (Box-folder 3: 33)
    - Law Must Replace War, undated (Box-folder 3: 34)
    - League to Enforce Peace, undated (Box-folder 3: 35)
    - Lyceum Alpinum, 1914 (Box-folder 3: 36)
    - The Massachussetts Peace Society, undated (Box-folder 3: 37)
    - The Measure of Victory, 1918 (Box-folder 3: 38)
    - New Books of Special Importance, 1914 (Box-folder 3: 39)
    - A New Era in Human History, 1917 (Box-folder 3: 40)
    - New Lectures Historical, Educational, Sociological, undated (Box-folder 3: 41)
    - The New Warfare in the Clouds, undated (Box-folder 3: 42)
    - The New World, undated (Box-folder 3: 43)
    - The Night Before Birth, 1916 (Box-folder 3: 44)
    - Official Documents Referring to the Circumstances That Led Up to the War, undated (Box-folder 3: 45)
    - Opere Pubblicate in Italia Sulla Guerra Mundiale 1914-1915 (Box-folder 3: 46)
    - Our Foreign and Home Relations in Trade Before and After the War, undated (Box-folder 3: 47)
    - People Not Awake to the Real Seriousness of this War, 1917 (Box-folder 3: 48)
    - Pilgrim Congregational Church, 1917 (Box-folder 3: 49)
    - Poland, 1917 (Box-folder 3: 50)
    - Preparedness, 1916 (Box-folder 3: 51)
    - Reading List on Great European War, 1914 (Box-folder 3: 52)
    - Repatriation Summary of Assistance and Benefits, 1918 (Box-folder 3: 53)
    - Ride to Berlin with the Canadian Mounted Rifles, undated (Box-folder 3: 54)
    - Selected Books on the European War, 1914 (Box-folder 3: 55)
    - The Society of Nations Versus Germany in the Case of Captain Fryatt, 1916 (Box-folder 3: 56)
    - The Story of the Red Triangle, undated (Box-folder 3: 57)
    - Ten Allies Costume Ball, undated (Box-folder 3: 58)
    - Timely Topics: Taking in Another Hole in the Muzzle Strap, 1916 (Box-folder 3: 59)
    - Timely Works of Direct and Related Interest on the European Situation, undated (Box-folder 3: 60)
    - To Arms, Citizens!, undated (Box-folder 3: 61)
    - To the President of the United States of America, Mr. Woodrow Wilson, Washington, 1916 (Box-folder 3: 62)
    - United States Government War Exposition, 1918 (Box-folder 3: 63)
    - Until Next Harvest, 1918 (Box-folder 3: 64)
    - Vues de Camps de Prisonniers, 1917 (Box-folder 3: 65)
    - War Books, undated (Box-folder 3: 66)
    - War Camp Community Service Song Sheet, undated (Box-folder 4: 1)
    - We Suggest, undated (Box-folder 4: 2)
    - What Australia Is Doing for Her Returned Soldiers, undated (Box-folder 4: 3)
    - What the Red Cross Is Going to Do, undated (Box-folder 4: 4)
    - What Women Can Do in the War, undated (Box-folder 4: 5)
    - Why the American Red Cross Needs a $100,000,000 War Fund at Once, undated (Box-folder 4: 6)
    - Winning the War, undated (Box-folder 4: 7)
    - Words without Deeds, 1916 (Box-folder 4: 8)
    - Zimmerman & Forshay, Members of the New York Stock Exchange, 1916 (Box-folder 4: 9)
    - $50,000,000 Imperial Russian Government External Loan, 1916 (Box-folder 4: 10)
  - Posters, 1917
    - "Take a Hand in Upbuilding the Nation's Defenses and Be an American!,", 1917 (Box-folder 4: 11)
  - Newspapers, 1917-1918
    - Clark University Library WWI poster collection, 1918 (Box-folder 5: 2)
    - General U.S. articles, 1917 (Box-folder 5: 3-4)
    - War Production Club--Canada, 1917 (Box-folder 5: 5)
    - War posters reproduced, 1917-1918 (Box-folder 5: 6)
    - Liberty loan advertisements, 1917 (Box-folder 5: 7-8)
    - Comic pictures, 1916-1917 (Box-folder 5: 9)
    - Victory loans--Canada, 1917 (Box-folder 5: 10)
    - The New York Herald, 1918 (Box-folder 5: 11)
    - The New York Times, 1918
    - The New York Times Review of Books, 1918
    - "United War Work Campaign,", 1918
  - Newspaper clippings, 1915-1918
    - "Dr. Eliot Wants a Long Lasting Alliance,", 1918 (Box-folder 4: 12)
    - "Harvard Making a Great Collection of War Literature,", 1918 (Box-folder 4: 13)
    - "French Relief Work Continued,", 1916 (Box-folder 4: 14)
    - "The Salle Des Rois at Rhems,", 1916 (Box-folder 4: 15)
    - Stewardson, Langdon, "Break Relations with Germany,", 1915 (Box-folder 4: 16)
    - Stewardson, Langdon, "Things Worse than War,", 1915 (Box-folder 4: 17)
    - "War Helps as Well as Harms,", 1916 (Box-folder 4: 18)
    - "Wilson Replies to Hertling and Czernin,", 1918 (Box-folder 4: 19)
    - "Wilson's Reply to Teutons,", 1918 (Box-folder 4: 20)
  - Leaflets, 1914-1918
    - "Avviso!,", undated (Box-folder 4: 21)
    - "Preparedness,", undated (Box-folder 4: 22)
    - "Davison Plans Big Campaign for Red Cross,", 1917 (Box-folder 4: 23)
    - "France-Amerique,", undated (Box-folder 4: 24)
    - "L'Ecureuil,", undated (Box-folder 4: 25)
    - Liberty Loan publications, 1917 (Box-folder 4: 26)
    - "The Little Citizens of Nancy,", undated (Box-folder 4: 27)
    - "New 'National' Review to Deal with 'America,'", undated (Box-folder 4: 28)
    - "Reparto Censura Militare Posta Estera,", 1918 (Box-folder 4: 29)
    - "The Societe des Concerts du Conservatoire,", 1918 (Box-folder 4: 30)
    - "To the People and Press of America,", 1914 (Box-folder 4: 31)
  - Miscellaneous, 1915-1919
    - American Committee for Armenian and Syrian Relief, 1916 (Box-folder 4: 32)
    - "The Case of Belgium: Summary of the Secret Documents,", undated (Box-folder 4: 33)
    - The Corporation Trust Company, 1918 (Box-folder 4: 34)
    - "Liberty Loan Publicity Bureau Press Releases,", 1917 (Box-folder 4: 35)
    - "Paraissant tous les Dimanches,", 1915 (Box-folder 4: 36)
    - The Spur Weekly, 1919 (Box-folder 4: 37)
    - Miscellaneous, 1916 (Box-folder 4: 38)